"Give me liberty or give me death."
&amp;quot; أعطني الحرية او أعطني الموت .
When Patrick Henry, the governor of Virginia,
عندما قال باتريك هنري , حاكم ولاية فرجنبا
said these words in 1775,
هذه الكلمات في عام 1775
he could never have imagined
لم يكن له أن يتخيل
just how much they would come to resonate
بمدى الصدى الذي سوف تحثه كلماته
with American generations to come.
لدى الاجيال الامريكة القادمة
At the time, these words were earmarked
في ذالك الوقت تلك الكلمات كانت موجهة
and targeted against the British,
ضد البريطانين
but over the last 200 years, they've come to embody
و لكن خلال السنوات المائتين الماضية هذه الكلمات اصبحت ترمز
what many Westerners believe,
الى ما ما يومن به الكثير من الغربيون
that freedom is the most cherished value,
بان الحرية هي أكثر القيم قداسة
and that the best systems of politics and economics
و بان افضل أنظمة السياسة و الاقتصاد
have freedom embedded in them.
مزروع فيها الكثير من قيم الحرية
Who could blame them?
من يحق له ان يلومهم ؟
Over the past hundred years, the combination
على مضى مئات السنين , المزج بين
of liberal democracy and private capitalism
الدمقراطية اللبرالية و الراس المالية الخاصة
has helped to catapult the United States
قد ساعد على نقل الولايات المتحدة
and Western countries
و الدول الغربية
to new levels of economic development.
الى اطوار جديدة من التطور الاقتصادي
In the United States over the past hundred years,
في الولايات المتحدة خلال المئة سنة الماضية
incomes have increased 30 times,
تضاعف الدخل تلاثون مرة
and hundreds of thousands of people
و مئات الاف من الناس
have been moved out of poverty.
خرجوا من مرحلة الفقر
Meanwhile, American ingenuity and innovation
في نفس الوقت , الابداع الامريكي و البراعة
has helped to spur industrialization
ساعدت في تحفيز الصناعات
and also helped in the creation and the building
و ساعدت في ابتكار و صناعة
of things like household appliances
اشياء مثل الاجهزة المنزلية
such as refrigerators and televisions,
مثل الثلاجات ,التلفزيونات,
motor vehicles and even the mobile phones in your pockets.
الدراجات النارية , و حتى الهواتف النقالة التي بداخل جيوبكم
It's no surprise, then, that even at the depths
لم يكن مفاجئا انذاك في خضم
of the private capitalism crisis,
ازمة الرأس مالية الخاصة
President Obama said,
قال الرئيس اوباما
"The question before us is not whether the market
السؤال الذي يواجهنا هو هل السوق
is a force for good or ill.
هو قوة اما للخير ام للشر
Its power to generate wealth and to expand freedom
بل القوة لزيادة الثروة و توسيع الحرية
is unmatched."
لا تتطابق
Thus, there's understandably
لذلك هناك
a deep-seated presumption among Westerners
اعتقاد عميق لدى الغربيون
that the whole world will decide to adopt
بان العالم سوف يقرر تبني
private capitalism as the model of economic growth,
الرأس المالية الخاصة كمثال للنمو الاقتصادي ,
liberal democracy, and will continue
الديمقراطية اللبرالية و سوف يستمرون
to prioritize political rights over economic rights.
في اعطاء الحقوق السياسية اولوية عن الحقوق الاقتصادية .
However, to many who live in the emerging markets,
لكن بالنسبة لهؤلاء الذين يعيشون في بلدان الاسواق الناشئة
this is an illusion, and even though
هذا مجرد وهم , مع ان
the Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
الميثاق العالمي لحقوق الانسان
which was signed in 1948,
و الذي وقع في 1948
was unanimously adopted,
تم تبنيه بالاجماع
what it did was to mask a schism
ما فعله كان اخفاء الأنقسام
that has emerged between developed and developing countries,
الذي حدث بين الدول المتقدمة و الدول الناشئة
and the ideological beliefs
و الاعتقادات الايدلوجية
between political and economic rights.
بين الحقوق السياسية و الاقتصادية
This schism has only grown wider.
هذا الانقسام زاد
Today, many people who live in the emerging markets,
اليوم الكثير ممكن يعيشون في بلدان الاسواق الناشئة ,
where 90 percent of the world's population lives,
حيث يعيش 90 في المئة من سكان العالم
believe that the Western obsession
يعتقدون بان الهاجس الغربي
with political rights is beside the point,
بالحقوق السياسة خارج عن الموضوع
and what is actually important
و أن المهم
is delivering on food, shelter,
هو تقديم الطعام و المأوى
education and healthcare.
و التعليم و الرعاية الصحية
"Give me liberty or give me death"
&amp;quot; أعطني الحرية او اعطني الموت &amp;quot;
is all well and good if you can afford it,
هي مقولة جيدة اذا كنت تقدر على دفع الثمن
but if you're living on less than one dollar a day,
و لكن اذا كنت تعيش باقل من دولار في اليوم
you're far too busy trying to survive
انت مشغول جدا بمحاولة الصمود
and to provide for your family
و توفير لقمة العيش لعائلتك
than to spend your time going around
من ان تقضي وقتك
trying to proclaim and defend democracy.
في محاولة نشر و الدفاع عن الدمقراطية
Now, I know many people in this room
الان ادرك بأن الكثير من الناس في هذه الغرفة
and around the world will think,
و حول العالم سوق يعتقدون
"Well actually, this is hard to grasp,"
بأن هذا صعب التصديق
because private capitalism and liberal democracy
لان الراسمالية الخاصة و الدمقراطية اللبرالية
are held sacrosanct.
مقدسة للغاية
But I ask you today, what would you do
و لكن اسالكم اليوم ماذا ستفعلون
if you had to choose?
اذا خيرتم
What if you had to choose
ماذا لو خيرتم
between a roof over your head
بين سقف فوق رؤوسكم
and the right to vote?
و الحق في التصويت
Over the last 10 years,
خلال العشر سنين الماضية
I've had the privilege to travel to over 60 countries,
لقد حظيت بالشرف للسفر الى اكثر من ستين دولة
many of them in the emerging markets,
العديد منها من دول الاسواق الناشئة
in Latin America, Asia,
في امريكا الاتينية ,اسيا
and my own continent of Africa.
و قارتي افريقيا
I've met with presidents, dissidents,
لقد قابلت العديد من الرؤساء , المعارضين
policymakers, lawyers, teachers,
, صناع القرار,المحامون,المدرسون
doctors and the man on the street,
الاطباء و عامة الشعب
and through these conversations,
و من خلال تلك المحادثات
it's become clear to me
كان واضحا لي
that many people in the emerging markets
بان العديد في دول الاسواق الناشئة
believe that there's actually a split occurring
يعتقدون بان هناك انقسام يحدث ايدولوجيا
between what people believe ideologically
بين ما يؤمن به الناس
in terms of politics and economics in the West
في ما يتعلق بالسيااسة و الاقتصاد في الغرب
and that which people believe in the rest of the world.
و ما يؤمن به العديد من الناس حول العالم
Now, don't get me wrong.
الآن، لا تفهموني خطأ.
I'm not saying people in the emerging markets
انا لا اقول بان الناس من دول الاسواق الناشئة
don't understand democracy,
لا يفهمون الدمقراطية
nor am I saying that they wouldn't ideally
و لا اقول بانهم لا يريدون
like to pick their presidents or their leaders.
انتقاء رؤسائهم و قادتهم بطريقة مثالية
Of course they would.
بالطبع هم يريدون ذالك
However, I am saying that on balance,
و لكن ما اقوله هو انهم
they worry more about
يشعرون بالقلق حول
where their living standard improvements are going to come from,
من اين سوف تاتي التحسينات لمستوى حياتهم
and how it is their governments can deliver for them,
و كيف سوف تقدم حكوماتهم تلك الخدمات لهم
than whether or not the government
اكثر من كون حكومتهم
was elected by democracy.
قد انخبت بطريقة دمقراطية ام لا
The fact of the matter
في حقيقة الأمر
is that this has become a very poignant question
لقد اصبح هذا السؤال مزعجا للغاية
because there is for the first time in a long time
لان هنالك للمرة الاولى منذ مدة طويلة
a real challenge to the Western ideological systems
تحدي حقيقي للانظمة الغربية والايدلوجية
of politics and economics,
المتعلقة بالسياسة و الاقتصاد
and this is a system that is embodied by China.
و هذا هو نظام مطبق في الصين
And rather than have private capitalism, they have state capitalism.
و بدلا من تبنيهم الرأسمالية الخاصة لقد تبنو رأسمالية الدولة
Instead of liberal democracy, they have de-prioritized the democratic system.
بدلا من الدمقراطية اللبرالية لم يجعلوا النظام الدمقراطي ذات اولية
And they have also decided to prioritize
و ايضا قررو وضع الاولية
economic rights over political rights.
للحقوق الاقتصادية على الحقوق السياسة
I put it to you today that it is this system
اقولها لكم اليوم بان هذا النظام
that is embodied by China
المطبق من قبل الصين
that is gathering momentum amongst people
هو الذي احدث زخما بين الناس
in the emerging markets as the system to follow,
في دول الاسواق الناشئة , بأنه النظام الذي يجب تطبيقه
because they believe increasingly
لانهم يعتقدون بصورة متزايدة
that it is the system
بأنه هو النظام
that will promise the best and fastest improvements
الذي يعد بافضل و اسرع التطورات
in living standards in the shortest period of time.
في الظروف الحياتية في وقت قصير جدا
If you will indulge me, I will spend a few moments
اذا اعرتموني انتباهكم سوف اقضي بعض اللحظات
explaining to you first
في محاولة التوضيح لكم اولا
why economically they've come to this belief.
لمذا هم اقتصاديا اصبحو يومنون بهذا
First of all, it's China's economic performance
اولا انه اداء الصين الاقتصادي
over the past 30 years.
خلال الثلاثون سنة الماضية
She's been able to produce record economic growth
استطاعت تحقيق نمو اقتصادي مذهل
and meaningfully move many people out of poverty,
و نقل الناس بطريقة هادفة خارج خط الفقر
specifically putting a meaningful dent in poverty
ووضع عراقيل ضد الفقر
by moving over 300 million people
بنقل اكثر من 300 مليون شخص
out of indigence.
خارج العوز و الحاجة
It's not just in economics,
ليست الاقتصاديات وحدها
but it's also in terms of living standards.
و لكن ايضا من حيث الظروف المعيشية
We see that in China, 28 percent of people
نرى في الصين , 28 بالمئة من الناس
had secondary school access.
كان لديهم الحق في التعليم الثانوي
Today, it's closer to 82 percent.
الان هذا الرقم اقرب الى 82 بالمئة
So in its totality, economic improvement
في مجمل الامر , التحسن الاقتصادي
has been quite significant.
كان كبير جدا
Second, China has been able
ثانيا , تمكنت الصين
to meaningfully improve its income inequality
من تحسين عدم المساواة في الدخل بطريقة هادفة
without changing the political construct.
بدون تغير البنية السياسية
Today, the United States and China
اليوم الولايات المتحدة و الصين
are the two leading economies in the world.
هما اكبر دولتين اقتصاديتين في العالم
They have vastly different political systems
لديهما نظامين سياسين مختلفين بشكل كبير
and different economic systems,
و ايضا انظمة اقتصادية مختلفة
one with private capitalism,
دولة بي راسمالية خاصة
another one broadly with state capitalism.
و اخرى بنظام راسمال دولة
However, these two countries
مع ذالك كلتا الدولتين لديهما
have the identical GINI Coefficient,
لديهما عامل &amp;quot;جيني&amp;quot; متطابق
which is a measure of income equality.
و هو مقياس يقيس المساواه في الدخل
Perhaps what is more disturbing
ولعل ما هو أكثر إثارة للقلق
is that China's income equality
ان المساواة في الدخل لدى الصين
has been improving in recent times,
قد تحسن في الاونة الاخيرة
whereas that of the United States
في حين ان المقياس في الولايات المتحدة
has been declining.
كان في تناقص
Thirdly, people in the emerging markets
ثالثا , الناس في دول الاسواق الناشئة
look at China's amazing and legendary
ينظرون الى التطور المذهل و الاسطوري
infrastructure rollout.
للبنية التحتية في الصين .
This is not just about China
ان الامر ليس بناء الصين
building roads and ports and railways
الطرق و السكك الحديدية و الموانئ
in her own country --
في بلدها
she's been able to build 85,000 kilometers
تمكنت من بناء 85,000 كيلومتر
of road network in China
من شبكة الطرق في الصين
and surpass that of the United States --
و الذي تعدت الولايات المتحدة
but even if you look to places like Africa,
و حتى اذا نظرت الى بعض الاماكن مثل افريقيا
China has been able to help tar the distance
لقد تمكنت الصين من المساعدة في زفلتة المسافة
of Cape Town to Cairo,
بين كيب تاون و القاهرة
which is 9,000 miles,
التي تقدر بي 9000 ميل
or three times the distance of New York to California.
او ثلاثةا ضعاف المسافة بين نيويورك الى كالفورنيا
Now this is something that people can see and point to.
و هذا شي يمكن ان يراه و يعلق عليه الناس
Perhaps it's no surprise
ربما لم يكن مفاجئا
that in a 2007 Pew survey, when surveyed,
حيث ظهر في استطلاع &amp;quot;بيو&amp;quot; الذي اجري عام 2007 و الذي شمل استطلاع
Africans in 10 countries said
الافارقة في 10 دول
they thought that the Chinese were doing
حيث اعتقدو بان الصينيون كانو يفعلون
amazing things to improve their livelihoods
اشياء مذهلة لتحسين حياتهم
by wide margins, by as much as 98 percent.
بفارق واسع، بنسبة تصل إلى 98 في المئة.
Finally, China is also providing innovative solutions
اخيرا , الصين ايضا تقدم حلولا ابتكارية
to age-old social problems that the world faces.
لمشاكل اجتماعية قديمة يواجهها العالم
If you travel to Mogadishu, Mexico City or Mumbai,
اذا سافرت الى مقديشو , و المكسيك او مومباي,
you find that dilapidated infrastructure and logistics
تجد ان البنية التحتية و الخدمات اللوجستيكية المتهالكة
continue to be a stumbling block
لا تزال عائقا
to the delivery of medicine and healthcare
لتقديم العلاج و الرعاية الصحية
in the rural areas.
في المناطق النائية
However, through a network of state-owned enterprises,
بالرغم من هذا , و عبر شركات مملوكة للدولة
the Chinese have been able to go into these rural areas,
تمكن الصينيون من الوصول الى تلك المناطق النائية
using their companies
مستخدمين شركاتهم
to help deliver on these healthcare solutions.
لللمساعدة في ايجاد حلول للرعاية الصحية
Ladies and gentlemen, it's no surprise
سيداتي سادتي , انها ليست مفاجئة
that around the world, people are pointing at what China is doing and saying,
بان الناس حول العالم يشيرون الى ما تقعله الصين و يقولون
"I like that. I want that.
احب ذلك , و اريد ذلك ,
I want to be able to do what China's doing.
اريد ان املك الاستطاعة للقيام بما تقوم به الصين
That is the system that seems to work."
هذا هو النظام الذي يبدو بانه ينجح .
I'm here to also tell you
انا ايضا هنا لكي اخبركم
that there are lots of shifts occurring
بأن هنالك الكثير من التغيرات التي تحدث
around what China is doing
حول ما تفعله الصين
in the democratic stance.
فيما يتعلق بمواقفها الدمقراطية
In particular, there is growing doubt
بالتحديد هنالك شك متزايد
among people in the emerging markets,
حول الناس في دول الاسواق الناشئة
when people now believe that democracy
حيث يعتقد الناس الان بأن الدمقراطية
is no longer to be viewed
لا يجب ان ينظر لها
as a prerequisite for economic growth.
كشرط اساسي للنمو الاقتصادي
In fact, countries like Taiwan, Singapore, Chile,
في الواقع، دول مثل تايوان وسنغافورة وشيلي
not just China, have shown that actually,
ليس فقط الصين , اظهرو بان بالفعل
it's economic growth that is a prerequisite
تقدمهم الاقتصادي هو شرط اساسي
for democracy.
للدمقراطية
In a recent study, the evidence has shown
في دراسة حديثة اظهر الدليل
that income is the greatest determinant
بان الدخل هو اعظم محدد
of how long a democracy can last.
الى مدة استمرار الدمقراطية
The study found that if your per capita income
لقد كشفت الدراسة بان لو كان نصيب الدخل من الفرد
is about 1,000 dollars a year,
حوالي الف دولار سنويا
your democracy will last about eight and a half years.
سوف تستمر الدمقراطية حوال ثمان سنين و نصف
If your per capita income is between
اذا كان نصيب الفرد من الدخل بين
2,000 and 4,000 dollars per year,
الفين و اربعة الاف دولار سنويا
then you're likely to only get 33 years of democracy.
سوف يحصلون تقريبا على 33 سنة من الدمقراطية فقط
And only if your per capita income
و فقط اذا كان نصيب الفرد من الدخل
is above 6,000 dollars a year
اعلى من ستة الاف دولار سنويا
will you have democracy come hell or high water.
سوف تحقق الدمقراطية مهما ساءت الظروف
What this is telling us
ما يخبرنا به هذا
is that we need to first establish a middle class
اننا نحتاج اولا الى بناء طبقة متوسطة
that is able to hold the government accountable.
يمكن ان تحاسب الحكومة
But perhaps it's also telling us
و لكن ربما يخبرنا ايضا
that we should be worried about going
باننا يجب ان نقلق من الذهاب
around the world and shoehorning democracy,
حول العالم و فرض الدمقراطية
because ultimately we run the risk
لاننا في النهاية سوف نخاطر
of ending up with illiberal democracies,
بالحصول على ديمقراطيات لبرالية
democracies that in some sense
دمقراطيات
could be worse than the authoritarian governments
يمكن ان تكون اسوأ من الحكومات الاستبداية
that they seek to replace.
الذين يحاولون تبديلها
The evidence around illiberal democracies
الدليل حول الدمقراطيات اللبرالية
is quite depressing.
محبط للغاية
Freedom House finds that although 50 percent
تجد منظمة فريدوم هاوس مع أن خمسين بالمئة
of the world's countries today are democratic,
من دول العالم دمقراطية
70 percent of those countries are illiberal
70 في المئة من هذه الدول غير لبرالية
in the sense that people don't have free speech
حيث ان الناس لا يتمتعون بحرية التعبير
or freedom of movement.
او حرية التنقل
But also, we're finding from Freedom House
و ايضا نجد من منظمة فريدوم هاوس
in a study that they published last year
في دراستهم التي نشرت العام الماضي
that freedom has been on the decline
تلك الحرية استمرت بالتناقص
every year for the past seven years.
سنويا في السنوات السبع الماضية
What this says
ما يقوله هذا
is that for people like me
انه لاشخاص مثلي
who care about liberal democracy,
الذين تهمهم الدمقراطية اللبرالية
is we've got to find a more sustainable way
بانه يجب ان نجد طريقة اكثر استدامة
of ensuring that we have a sustainable form
لضمان ان يكون هنالك نوع اكثر استدامة
of democracy in a liberal way,
للدمقراطية بطريقة لبرالية
and that has its roots in economics.
و جذوره مغروسة بمبدأ الاقتصاد
But it also says that as China moves
و ايضا يقول ان الصين تتقدم
toward being the largest economy in the world,
نحو ان تكون البلد الاقتصادي الاكبر في العالم
something that is expected to happen
شيء يتوقع ان يحدث
by experts in 2016,
بحلول العام 2016 بواسطة الخبراء
that this schism between the political
بأن الانقسام بين السياسة
and economic ideologies of the West and the rest
و الايدولجيات الاقتصادية للغرب و البقية
is likely to widen.
سوف يزداد على الارجح
What might that world look like?
كيف يمكن ان يبدو ذاك العالم
Well, the world could look like
سوف يبدو العالم مثل
more state involvement and state capitalism;
المزيد من تدخل الدولة و رأسمالية الدولة
greater protectionisms of nation-states;
مزيد من الحماية الاقتصادية من الدول القومية
but also, as I just pointed out a moment ago,
و ايضا كما اشرت اليه قبل قليل
ever-declining political rights
حقوق سياسية متراجعة
and individual rights.
و ذات الشيء للحقوق الفردية
The question that is left for us in general
السؤال المطروح عموما
is, what then should the West be doing?
هو ما هو الذي يجب ان يفعله الغرب
And I suggest that they have two options.
و انا اقترح لهم خيارين
The West can either compete or cooperate.
الغرب يمكن ان ينافس او يتعاون
If the West chooses to compete with the Chinese model,
اذا قرر الغرب التنافس مع النموذج الصيني
and in effect go around the world
و كرد فعل يجوب انحاء العالم
and continue to try and push an agenda
و يستمر بالمحاولة في دفع مخطط
of private capitalism and liberal democracy,
الرأسمالية الخاصة و الدمقراطية اللبرالية
this is basically going against headwinds,
و الذي يحدث ضد الرياح
but it also would be a natural stance
ولكنه أيضا سيكون موقفا الطبيعية
for the West to take
لان يتخذه الغرب
because in many ways it is the antithesis
لانه من نواحي كثيرة نفيض
of the Chinese model
النموذج الصيني
of de-prioritizing democracy, and state capitalism.
من حيث عدم اعطاء الدمقراطية و الراسمالية القومية الاولوية
Now the fact of the matter is,
الآن حقيقة الأمر هي،
if the West decides to compete,
اذا قرر الغرب بأن ينافس
it will create a wider schism.
سوف يقوم بزيادة الانقسام
The other option is for the West to cooperate,
الخيار الاخر هو ان يتعاون الغرب
and by cooperating I mean
بالتعاون اعني
giving the emerging market countries the flexibility
اعطاء دول الاسواق الناشئة المرونة
to figure out in an organic way
للمعرفة بطريقة عضوية
what political and economic system
ما هو النظام السياسي و الاقتصادي
works best for them.
الذي يعمل بشكل أفضل بالنسبة لهم.
Now I'm sure some of you in the room
انا متأكدة بان البعض منكم في هذه القاعة
will be thinking, well, this is like ceding to China,
سوف يفكرون بأن هذا مثل التنازل الى الصين
and this is a way, in other words,
و هذه وسيلة , و بعبارة اخري
for the West to take a back seat.
تجعل من الغرب يجلس في المقعد الخلفي
But I put it to you
و لكني اقولها لكم
that if the United States and European countries
اذا الولايات المتحدة و الدول الاوربية
want to remain globally influential,
ارادو الاستمرار بأن يكونوا مصدر تاثير عالمي
they may have to consider cooperating
يجب عليهم ان يفكروا في التعاون
in the short term in order to compete,
على المدى القصير من اجل التنافس
and by that, they might have to focus
و بفعل ذلك سوف يتوجب عليهم التركيز
more aggressively on economic outcomes
بطريقة أكثر إقداما على النتائج الاقتصادية
to help create the middle class
للمساعدة في تكوين طبقة متوسطة
and therefore be able to hold government accountable
و تبعا لذالك تحميل الحكومة المسئولية
and create the democracies that we really want.
و تكوين الدمقراطيات الذي يريدونها حقا
The fact of the matter is that
حقيقة الامر هي
instead of going around the world
بدلا من الذهاب حول العالم
and haranguing countries for engaging with China,
و وعظ الدول التي تتعامل مع الصين
the West should be encouraging its own businesses
يجب على الغرب تشجيع صناعته الخاصة
to trade and invest in these regions.
للتجارة و الاستثمار في تلك المناطق
Instead of criticizing China for bad behavior,
بدلا من انتقاد الصين بسبب السلوك السئ
the West should be showing how it is
يجب على الغرب ان يظهر كيف
that their own system of politics and economics
ان نظامهم السياسي و الاقتصادي
is the superior one.
هو الاكثر تفوقا
And instead of shoehorning democracy
و بدلا من فرض الدمقراطية
around the world,
حول العالم
perhaps the West should take a leaf
ربما يجب على الغرب اخذ العبرة من
out of its own history book
تاريخهم
and remember that it takes a lot of patience
و ان يتذكروا بأنه يتطلب الكثير من الصبر
in order to develop the models
من اجل تطوير النماذج
and the systems that you have today.
و الانظمة التي تمتلكونها اليوم
Indeed, the Supreme Court Justice Stephen Breyer
بالفعل , ذكرنا ستيفين برير قاضي المحكمة العليا
reminds us that it took the United States
انه تتطلب الولايات المتحدة
from the time that the Constitution was written
من وقت كتابة الدستور
for there to be equal rights in the United States.
لكي يكون لديها حقوق مساوية
Some people would argue that today
بعض الناس قد يجادل بأن اليوم
there is still no equal rights.
لا يوجد حقوق متساوية
In fact, there are groups who would argue
في الواقع، هناك بعض المجموعات التي تزعم
that they still do not have equal rights under the law.
أنهم ما زالوا لا يتمتعون بحقوق متساوية في ظل القانون.
At its very best,
في افضل حالاته
the Western model speaks for itself.
النموذج الغربي يتحدث عن نفسه
It's the model that put food on the table.
انه النموذج الذي يضع الطعام على الطاولة
It's the refrigerators.
انها الثلاجات
It put a man on the moon.
لقد وضع الرجل على سطع الفمر
But the fact of the matter is,
و لكن حقيقة الامر هي
although people back in the day
بالرغم من ان الناس في الماضي
used to point at the Western countries and say,
كانو يشيرون الى الدول الغربية و يقولو
"I want that, I like that,"
&amp;quot; أريد ذالك , احب ذالك &amp;quot;
there's now a new person in town
هناك الآن شخص جديد في المدينة
in the form of a country, China.
في هيئة دولة , الصين
Today, generations are looking at China
اليوم الاجيال تنظر الى الصين
and saying, "China can produce infrastructure,
و تقول الصين يمكنها انشاء البنى التحتية
China can produce economic growth,
الصين يمكنها ان تحقق النمو الاقتصادي
and we like that."
و نحن نحب ذالك
Because ultimately, the question before us,
لان السؤال المطروح امامنا
and the question before
و السؤال المطروح
seven billion people on the planet
امام سبعة مليار شخص
is, how can we create prosperity?
هو، كيف يمكننا تحقيق الازدهار؟
People who care and will pivot towards the model
الاشخاص المهتمون سوف يتمحورون حول هذا النموذج
of politics and economics
السياسي و الاقتصادي
in a very rational way,
بطريقة عقلانية جدا
to those models that will ensure
لهؤلاء سوف يضمن هذا النموذج
that they can have better living standards
معاير معيشية افضل
in the shortest period of time.
في أقصر فترة من الزمن.
As you leave here today,
و انتم مغادرون اليوم
I would like to leave you
اريد ان اترككم
with a very personal message,
مع رسالة شخصية جدا
which is what it is that I believe
و هو الشي الذي اعتقد
we should be doing as individuals,
أننا يجب ان نفعله كأفراد
and this is really about being open-minded,
و هذا حقا يتمحور حول ان نكون منفتحي العقل
open-minded to the fact that our hopes and dreams
منفتحين حول الواقع بان امالنا و احلامنا
of creating prosperity for people around the world,
بتحقيق الازدهار و الرفاهية للناس حول العالم
creating and meaningfully putting a dent in poverty
تحقيق و وضع العراقيل بطريقة هادفة على الفقر
for hundreds of millions of people,
لمئات الملايين من الناس
has to be based in being open-minded,
يجب ان يكون مبنيا على الانفتاح
because these systems have good things
لان تلك الانظمة تمتلك أشياء جيدة
and they have bad things.
و اشياء سيئة
Just to illustrate,
فقط للتلخيص
I went into my annals of myself.
لقد بحثت في تاريخ حياتي
That's a picture of me.
انها صورة لي
Awww. (Laughter)
اوووه ( ضحك)
I was born and raised in Zambia in 1969.
لقد ولدت و ترعرت في زامبيا في عام 1969
At the time of my birth,
في الوقت الذي ولدت فيه،
blacks were not issued birth certificates,
لم تكن شهادات الميلاد تصدر للاشخاص السود
and that law only changed in 1973.
و لم يتغير هذا القانون الا في عام 1973
This is an affidavit from the Zambian government.
هذه شهادة خطية من الحكومة الزامبية.
I bring this to you to tell you that in 40 years,
احمل هذا لكم لاخبركم يانه في اربعين عاما
I've gone from not being recognized as a human being
انتقلت من عدم الاعتراف بي كأنسانة
to standing in front of the illustrious TED crowd today
الى وقوفي اليوم امام حشد (TED) اللامع
to talk to you about my views.
لاخبركم عن معتقداتي
In this vein, we can increase economic growth.
في هذا السياق يمكن ان نزيد النمو الاقتصادي
We can meaningfully put a dent in poverty.
يمكن ان نضع العراقيل على الفقر يطريقة هادفة
But also, it's going to require
و لكنه ايضا سوف يتتطلب
that we look at our assumptions,
ان ننظر الى افتراضاتنا
assumptions and strictures that we've grown up with
الافتراضات و القيود التي كبرنا معها
around democracy, around private capitalism,
حول الدمقراطية , حول الرأسمالية الخاصة
around what creates economic growth
حول ما يخلق النمو الاقتصادي
and reduces poverty and creates freedoms.
و ما ينقص الفقر و يولد الحريات
We might have to tear those books up
ربما يجب علينا ان نمزق تلك الكتب
and start to look at other options
و البدء بالبحث عن خيارات اخرى
and be open-minded to seek the truth.
و ان نصبع منفتحين نحو الحصول على الحقيقة
Ultimately, it's about transforming the world
في نهاية المطاف، انه يتمحور حول تحويل العالم
and making it a better place.
و جعله مكانا افضل
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)